本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
Volken did it?
ヴォルケンか？
They're saying he made off with
Ylucklucu and left Bantorra.
ユックユックを盗んでバントーラを飛び出たらしいぞ
Seriously? With a war-machine of the past?
まじかよ　追憶の戦機を…
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
I refuse to believe he did such a thing!
あの子がそんなことをするはずがありません
御寝小をしたシーツを隠しても
Even when he hides his sheets
after wetting the bed,
罪悪感からすぐに白状するような子なんですよ
his guilty conscience always
makes him confess!
Uh... How long ago was that?
えーと　それいつのごろの話ですか？
They brought him here as a baby,
so he grew up in the Library.
あいつは赤ん坊のごろで拾われて
この図書館ででかくなったからな
I refuse to believe it!
私は信じませんよ
It's not unheard of, though.
でもありがちですよね
世間しらずの温室育ちほど
It's always the sheltered ones who act out.
やばいこと仕出かすって言うか
He is always fighting
with the Acting Director.
ずっと代行に反発してたし
す…すいません　イレイアさん
M-My apologies, Ireia!
こいつシューときますので
Stop! I'm gonna vomit!
I'll strangle him for you!
What's all this commotion?
何を騒いでるの？
You're supposed to be working!
今は就業中です
Get back to your posts and
resume work at once!
それぞれの持ち場に戻り　速やかに仕事を再開するように
You, too, Ireia. Don't get caught
up in all these rumors.
イレイアさんも　噂に振り回されずにいてください
そ…そうよね
Y-You're right.
Huh? Milepoc...
あれ？　ミレボッくさん
うん？
Hmm?
上着逆
Your jacket's on backwards.
What does it matter, as long
as it keeps me warm!
服は寒さを凌ぎ機能性に優れていればそれでいいの
You have a problem?!
問題が？！
い…いえ
N-No...
I've never seen someone so obviously
freaking out in my entire life.
あんなに分かりやすく動揺してる人　初めて見た
It's because Milepoc and Volken
joined in the same group.
ミレポックとヴォルケンは同期だからな
I'm sure right now, she has
a lot going on in her head.
まぁ　いろいろと思うとこがあるんだろう
A lot going on in general...
それこそ　いろいろな
The one who stops is foolish
止まる者　愚かなりし
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
A piece of black wing gently touches fingers
诸
神字幕组
君が一つの　物語なら
If you were a story
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
You could still rewrite it all you want
血のインクは乾かない
The ink of blood doesn't dry up
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
No one knows the real us
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
What changes the chaotic world
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
What we pursued isn't
Small happiness
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Fight with a rumbling heartbeat as a sign
意のまま　進めば
What awaits you is infinite if you
move forward as you wish
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Fight off no matter how many
times you get defeated
幾度と　汚れと
Engrave your dream onto the scar you bear
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
In order to connect today's memory that's
on the verge of being buried to tomorrow
Episode 5
A Betrayal, a Cup, and a Meandering Path
第5话 背叛与杯和迷途之径
トアット鉱山で見つかったルイモンの「本」が
Luimon's Book was stolen in transit,
after it was found at the Toatt Mine.
移送中に何者かに盗まれた
犯人は恐らく…
We suspect...
神溺教団…ですね
The Church of Drowning
in God's Grace, right?
あ
Yes.
It's extremely rare to dig up the Book of
someone connected to the Church,
教団員はおろか
やつらに関わった人間の「本」はめったに発掘されることがない
let alone a Church member.
Luimon's Book might be the key to
unraveling the Church's mysteries.
ルイモンの「本」は教団の謎を紐解く鍵にもなるだろう
Luimon really looked out for me.
ルイモンに私　本当にお世話になりましたから
I'm going to give this 110 percent!
あたし頑張ります！
I won't return to the Library until
I've recovered Luimon's Book!
ルイモンの「本」を奪い返すまで図書館には帰りません
Noloty!
ノロティ
Milepoc.
ミレボッくさん
いい？
Listen. Contact us via telepathy
as soon as you arrive.
まず現地に到着したら「思考共有」を
毎晩の報告も忘れないで
Make sure to report in, every night.
はい　ありがとうございます
I will. Thank you.
なぜ代行もあなたにこんな重大の任務を
Why is the Acting Director sending
you on such a critical mission?
And alone? Is this really a good idea?
それも一人でなんて
本当に大丈夫なのか？
大丈夫ですか？
Are you all right?
うっ　なにが？
Why do you ask?
目…赤いですよ
Your eyes are red...
Is everything okay?
どうかしました？
私の目が赤いことであなたに不利益は生まれるとでも？
Will my eyes being red handicap
you or something?
O-Of course not.
い…いえ
We're down a flying boat,
thanks to you-know-who.
どこかの坊やのせいで　飛行艇も不足してるな
I'll send several Librarians to go investigate.
司書数人も捜査に向かわせてます
We'll spot them in no time.
発見されるのも時間の問題です
Ylucklucu used to be in the
Church's possession.
ユックユックは神溺教団の保持していたものだ
What Volken did bolsters
our enemy, the Church.
ヴォルケンが仕出かしたことは神溺教団への利敵行為に繋がる
捕まれば　重罪…か
He'll probably be executed for
treason, if he's caught.
どうしてなの？
Why did you do it?
聞こえるなら返事をして
If you can hear this, please answer me.
いえ！返事をなさい！
No, you must answer me!
Volken Macmani!
ヴォルケン＝マクマーニ！
ヴォルケン…
Volken...
You're no fool, Acting Director.
あんたも相当のもんじゃの　代行
わしの「聖浄眼」でヴォルケンの魂の色を確かめておけなんて
But asking me to use my Sacred Eyes
to see Volken's true character?
ほのからあいつが仕出かすことを見越してたのか
Were you expecting him to
do what he did, all along?
前置きはいいから
Cut to the chase, will ya?
やつの相は直　志向は理想　望みは正義じゃった
His dominant trait is honesty, his thoughts are
of his ideals, and he wishes for justice.
とても反乱を起す器じゃない
By no means is he the rebel type.
I figured as much.
やっぱりね　どこまでいっても正義の味方なのよね
No matter where he goes, he'll always
be a defender of justice.
ヴォルケン君は
Mr. Volken...
あ？
Huh?
What's Milepoc up to?
ミレボは　どうしてる？
「聖浄眼」なんぞわざわざ使わんでも　分かるわー
I can tell you that without
using my Sacred Eyes.
Betrayal...
裏切り…分からない
I don't understand it.
ずっと隣にいたはずなのに
He was always right there, beside me.
So how could he do that?
なぜ彼があんなことをしたのか
Also...
そして　彼が残していったもの
Why did he leave this behind?
Lascall is a mysterious, mysterious
proprietor of Books.
ラスコールは不思議な不思議な本屋さんです
不思議な力で「本」を集め　世界を飛び回ります
He gathers Books with his obscure
power and flies around the globe.
そして　恋する少女が思いを伝えられず命を落としたとき
Then, when girls die, having never told
the person they love their feelings,
その「本」を思い人へと届けてあげるのです
he delivers their Book to their beloved.
これは…
This is...
おー　自惚れちゃって
Oh... How vain!
お前が死んだなら　きっときっとラスコール＝オセロの手によって
"Upon your death,
by the power of Lascall Othello,
your Book will be brought to be with me!"
俺の元に「本」が運ばれてくるだろう　で？
Upon my death?
What are you talking about?
私が死ぬ？　どういうことです
えっ？　あー
No. You see, that's not the problem here...
だからさ　問題はそこじゃなくて
As an Armed Librarian, I take matters
of life and death very seriously.
武装司書としてその生死は大きな問題となりますわ
ねぇ　なんて言えばいいかな？
How can I put this...
Oh, I know!
そうだ
North, in the Library's fourth labyrinth, row E-25,
図書迷宮第四階層北のA－25番に今のあんたにぴったりの「本」があるよ
is the simply perfect Book for you.
Perfect for me?
私に…ぴったりの？
You should study up on these
a bit more, like I have...
ちょっとはさ…　あんたもこの手のことを勉強して…
So you're saying that if I read it,
それを読めば
ヴォルケンがバントーラに背いた一端が理解できるというのですね
I'll understand why Volken
betrayed Bantorra, right?
No.
いや…
Thank you for the information!
情報　ありがとうございます
大丈夫かな
Is she gonna be okay?
Bantorra Library is divided into six
libraries and five labyrinths.
バントーラ図書館は六つの書庫と五つの迷宮で構成されている
The Age of Paradise, when
the Gods ruled mankind...
神々が人間を治めていた楽園時代
It was an era of true peace,
without war, poverty, or crime.
戦争はもちろん　貧困や犯罪もなく　平和そのものだった
However, the Gods fled the earth.
しかし　神々が地上から去ることとなる
「過去神--バントーラ」は自らが作り出した図書館に封印された
The God of the Past, Bantorra, was sealed
within the Library He had created.
He left the task of running
the Library to the humans.
その図書館の管理を人間に任せて
And such was the birth of
the Armed Librarians.
それが武装司書の始まり
The Armed Librarians were to excavate
the Books, maintain them,
武装司書に与えられた仕事は「本」の発掘　管理
and destroy any who would do them harm.
本に災いをなすものたちの駆逐
そして
And...
The main reason we're called
"Armed Librarians"...
私たちが武装司書と呼ばれる　もっともたる故
That's not fair! Stay away!
いやだ　あんたずるいよ　おいてかないで！
Bantorra unleashed beasts in the Library to
protect the Books from intruders:
侵入者から「本」を守るため
バントーラが図書館に嵌った獣――「衛獣」
Guardian Beasts.
Only those who can make it past their guard
are qualified to protect the Books.
彼らの警護を突破できる者でなければ　「本」を扱う資格はない
M-Milepoc?
ミ…ミレボッくさん
You're apprentices, aren't you?
あなたたち見習いね
Do you really think you can become
Armed Librarians if you're struggling against
第五階層の「衛獣」――「針毛狼」に苦戦して
the Guardian Beast, Wolfclaw,
in the fifth library?
武装司書になれると思う？
S-Sorry. This is our first field drill.
す…すいません　初めての実地訓練で
ならば　もっと南を選びなさい
Then choose a place farther south!
あの辺りなら「騎兵」レバルしか現れない
You'll only face cavalry-level ones there.
Y-Yes, ma'am!
はい
The Guardian Beasts become much stronger
as you descend into libraries four and five.
「衛獣」は第五階層　第四階層と下るごとに強さを増す
Also, the more important
Books are stored there.
それとともに　収められている「本」の重要度も上がる
Mokkania!
モッカニアさん
Ants...
蟻…踏んだら殺す
Huh?
You'll kill them if you step on them.
It's snack time. Eat up.
おやつの時間だ　食べろ
糖分が不足すれば　判断力も鈍る
Your ability to make decisions dulls
as your blood sugar drops.
Um...
あの…
鈍っている顔をしている
They look dull now.
え？
Huh?
あ…ありがとうございます
Th-Thank you very much.
A－25番　A－25
E-25... E-25...
This is it.
これで
ああ～ 気づかなかった！
Ah! I had no idea that the one I've been
looking for was beside me all along!
本当に大切な人が　こんな近くにいたなんて
俺もだよ
I feel the same! Oh, love hides itself in sin!
愛とはなんて惚けな罪作りなんだ
But you're going to leave
me behind, are you not?
でもあなたはあたしをおいて去ってしまうでしょう
Nonsense!
ばかなこと
距離　時間も関係ない
Distance and time do not apply to us.
For love is eternal.
愛は死なないんだ
ああ…あなた
Oh, dear!
これが？　どうして必要　私に？
This?! Why did I need to see that?!
ハ…破廉恥
H-How shameless!
The Book!
「本」が…
あの…
Excuse me...
あー　はい
Oh, right, right.
お待たせしました
Thank you for waiting.
This is the Book you reserved.
こちらがご叱正の「本」になります
Oh, dear...
あー　あなた…
この「本」は第五封印指定を受けています
This Book has been assigned a #5 seal.
書庫外に持ち出すことは固く禁じられています
Removing it from the premises
is strictly prohibited.
違反の際には「虚構抹殺杯アーガックス」による記憶抹消　及び…
If you are found in violation of that rule,
your memories will be erased by the
fantasy-slaughter device Argax,
and...
いや　野暮はなしだな
Enough with that stuff.
ばあさん　ここにサインを
Please sign here, ma'am.
はい
Certainly.
マットさん　マットさん
Matt! Matt!
ヴォルケン？
Volken?
おー　どうした？
Oh, what's up?
見て見て　これ
Look at this!
ご…ごめんなさい
I-I'm sorry...
What's the matter with you, Volken?
なにをしている　ヴォルケン
フォトナ代行
Acting Director Fotona.
My sincere apologies. Are you hurt?
申し訳ない　お怪我は？
Oh, no. I'm fine, thank you.
いいえ　なんともありませんから
あ…あの…
U-Um...
図書館という神聖な場所で　お前は何をしている
The Library is a sacred place.
What do you think you're doing?
え…えっと…あの…
U-Um...
Er...
人の死は　悲しまなくてはならない
People's deaths are to be mourned.
Human life itself should be exalted.
人が生きることは　喜ばなくてはならない
それは人でなくとも同じこと
And that applies to all life,
not just humans.
武装司書を目指すのならば
If you wish to become an Armed Librarian,
you must treat all living things with respect.
全ての生を　蔑ろにするな
Oh, hello.
あら
まっ　ありがとうね
Thank you.
さっき　痛くなかった？
You weren't hurt before?
大丈夫よ
I'm fine, really.
それにしてもね
The Acting Director shouldn't
have gotten so angry, too.
代行様もそんなに怒ることじゃないのに
ううん　フォトナさんは間違ってない
Oh, no. Fotona is absolutely right.
I hope to become an Armed
Librarian like him someday.
僕は　フォトナさんみたいな武装司書になりたいんだ
なれますよ　あなたならね
Then I'm sure you will become one.
うん！
Yeah!
He was no different back then.
私の知っているヴォルケンと　何も変わらない
彼らは人間だ！
They were and still are human!
どこまでもまっすぐで
He's so straightforward.
痣のあとは　残らなくてよかったな
I'm glad the bruising didn't
leave any scars.
どこまでも　不器用で
And so awkward, in his own way...
でも　現実に彼はバントーラを裏切った
But the truth is that he betrayed Bantorra.
ここは？
Where am I?
いけない　ここは第四階層
This is bad. I'm in the fourth library.
「象兵」？
An Elephant Guardian!
だめ　私…今は…
I'm...
done for...
Volken?
ヴォルケン？
ヴォルケン！
Volken!
Matt?
マットさん
Sorry I'm not Volken.
ヴォルケンじゃなくて　残念だったな
What's the matter?
どうした？
若い頃のマットさん　長髪が似合ってませんでした
You looked bad with long hair, as a kid.
ああ　見殺しにしとけばよかったか
Oh? Maybe I should have
let you die, after all.
大体　ヴォルケンは勘違えしてるわ
Volken just has the wrong idea!
He still puts honey into his tea, like a kid!
蜂蜜ずきて　餓鬼じてのくせに
何を飲ませたんだ？
What did you give her to drink?
へへ　シュースみたいなもんですよ
Just something like juice.
Betraying Bantorra is an unforgivable
offense for an Armed Librarian.
武装司書たる者　バントーラに背くことは許されないのよ
例え　どんな理由があったとしても
No matter what the reason!
そう　そう　甘ちゃんなんですよね
Exactly. He's such a baby.
お前なぁ…
Don't encourage her.
それに戦友を蔑ろにするなんて　私に一言もなしで
And he left his comrade-in-arms high and dry,
without saying a word to me...
そうですよ　本当はあいつは　最低の男ですよ
I know, right?
He's a complete jerk.
ヴォルケンは最低なんかじゃない
Don't call Volken a jerk!
正義感があって　若草色の髪も美しくて
He has a sense of righteousness and
beautiful hair, the color of fresh grass.
And out in battle... He was one
of the best among our class...
戦闘の腕だって　同期の中で…
いえ　武装司書の中でも指折りで
No, among all the Armed Librarians!
And he loved honey.
蜂蜜が　大好きで
誰にでも　優しくて
And he was kind to everyone.
不器用なくらい　まっすぐで
And he was straightforward
to the point of awkwardness.
そんな…そんなヴォルケンが
That...
That's the Volken I...
私は…
私は？
You?
私は…
I...
こちらでよろしいですか？
Will this do?
あ　ちょっと　どうしたんですか？
あ　頼む
Yes, please.
Hey! What's going on?
あ　ミ…ミレボッくさん
Milepoc!
やっと気付いたのか
You just figured that out?
鈍いにも　ほどがあるな
Dullness knows no bounds.
ほーあ　本日のお仕事終わり！
Another day's work is done!
Now, one drink before I hit the hay...
さっ　寝しなに一杯ひっかけて…
こんばんは
Good evening!
うん？　ミレボ？
Milepoc?
何なの　この時間に？
What are you doing here at this hour?
ほぉー　酒臭い
Ugh. You reek of booze.
Milepoc Finedel, entering.
ミレポック＝ファインデル入ります
もう入ってんじゃないのよ
Uh, you already entered.
代行　このたびは
Acting Director, I've come here tonight
追憶の戦機--「虚構抹殺杯アーガックス」の使用を 認めていただきたく参りました
to ask for your permission to let me
use the war-machine of the past,
the fantasy-slaughter device, Argax.
なんで？
Why?
まさかヴォルケンの記憶だけ消し去りたいとか
Don't tell me you wanna do something girly,
like erasing all your memories of Volken?
乙女なこと考えてる
ふーん？
What's this? You don't trust him?
ミレボはあいつを信用してあげないんだ
いや
No...
You don't have to save your
chastity for Bantorra.
別にさぁ
バントーラに操を捧げなくたっていいのよ
反逆者に惚れてたって　業務に差し支えなきゃ
As long as you don't let it interfere with your
work, who cares if you're in love with a traitor?
あたしは別になーんともないわ
I sure don't, that's for sure.
惚れ…
I-In love?
違うの？
You're not?
いえ　違いない…
N-No, I'm not...
いいえ　惚れる惚れないは関係ありません
No! Whether or not I'm
in love isn't the point!
ただ…
I just...
ただ？
You just?
もう　揺れたくはない
I'm sick of hesitating.
この精神状態では
I realized that
my current state of mind will begin to interfere
with my work as an Armed Librarian!
武装司書の仕事を続けることが困難であると考えました
So please, Acting Director...
お願いします　代行
そう
I see.
許可してよかったのか？
Should you have let her use it?
アーガックスは基本　封印指定の「本」を読んだものと
Argax is only to be used to erase
the memories of criminals
and people who read sealed Books...
罪人の記憶を消す場合にしか…
I had no choice. She's dense.
しかたないじゃない　あの子は頭固いし
それに　愛ってのは時に真理に近づいちゃったりするからね
Also,
sometimes love can get close
to the truth, you know?
え？
なに　可愛い部下が心配？
What? You're worried about
your beloved subordinate?
いいえ
No.
さってと
All righty, then!
絶対ヴォルケン　代行となんかあったんだよ
There was something going on between
Volken and the Acting Director.
代行って　なに考えてた分からないし
Who knows what the Acting
Director is thinking?
シー　触覚糸で代行に聞かれたらどうすんだよ
Shh! What'll you do if she hears
you with her sensory threads?
いた…
Ow!
代行
A-Acting Director!
あんたたち雑魚の噂話なんてわざわざ盗み聞きしないわよ
I would never listen to two nobodies
like you telling each other rumors.
やっぱり聞いてる
She was listening!
これ盗み聞きじゃなくて　立ち聞き
But not eavesdropping.
I just happened to overhear it.
それでもって　命令
Now, time to give orders.
さあ　消したい記憶を杯に向けて囁き　一息に飲み干すのです
Whisper what you'd like to forget into
the cup, then drink it all at once.
これから　ヴォルケンの話はミレボの前では禁句
You are no longer to mention
Volken in front of Milepoc.
ヴォルケン＝マクマーニの記憶
My memories of Volken Macmani and...
そして　彼への感情の　すべてを…
All of my feelings for him.
いいわね　ほかの皆にもあんたたち得意の噂話で伝えてちょうだい
Got it?
Go use that rumor-spreading skill you're
so good at to inform the others.
Y-Yes, ma'am.
はい
でも　なぜ…
But why?
OK？
Okay?
OKです
Okay!
はあ　手間かけさせてくれるわ
They're always making me work.
恋…ねえ
Love, huh?
なにをしているんです？
What do you think you're doing?
ルイークさんには第四書庫の整理をお任せしましたよね
Didn't I ask you to sort
the fourth library?
R-Right, but Ireia's tea was so good...
お…おー
いや　イレイアさんのお紅茶が美味しくて　つい…
なんか昨日とは違うような…
Something about her has changed
since yesterday.
R-Right, but Ireia's tea was so good...
服もちゃんと着てるし
She has her clothes on
straight, for starters.
なに？
What?
Oh, nothing! We're off!
あっ　いや　行ってきます
ミレボッくさん　紅茶はどう？
Would you like some tea, Milepoc?
いいえ　私は仕事が…
Oh, no. I have work to do.
急ぎのものはないでしょう？
But you're in no hurry, right?
あっはー
R-Right.
Thank you.
どうも　イレイアさん蜂蜜はあります？
Oh, Ireia, do you have any honey?
ええ？
Huh?
甘いのを好きだった？
You take your tea sweet?
いいえ　いつもはほしくないんですけど
No, I usually don't.
なんとなく　今日は
But today, for some reason, I do.
そう
I see...
Lost the light
Before closing the sun
If it's a sparkling storm
Jump in before it tempts
The end comes to everyone one day
When the day comes
Aim for the future that begins to move
Even if it's already been written
Search and even acquire the
meaning of getting hurt
In order to be myself
Thunder,
バントーラに現れた黄金の怪物
A golden monster appears within Bantorra.
Thunder, a Monster,
無慈悲な雷は
Merciless thunder slices through
the peace built on falsehoods.
偽りの安眠を切り裂いた
雷电与怪物和搏斗的少女
Thunder, a Monster, and a Girl's Punch
Merciless thunder slices through
the peace built on falsehoods.